Guide to the Eberhardt Ober Brewing Company Records, 1883-1897 AIS.1994.07a
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company Records
1883-1897
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company
AIS.1994.07a
5.88 Linear Feet (3 boxes & 1 oversized folder)
This collection contains correspondecne and receipts for the Eberhardt Ober Brewing Company of Allegheny City, Pa. (now North Side, Pittsburgh), 1883-1897.
History
The Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company was established in Allegheny City, Pa. (now Pittsburgh's North Side), in 1883 by two men of German brewing families. William Eberhardt was born in Alsace France, April 20, 1844, and emigrated with his parents to Allegheny City in 1846. Conrad Eberhardt, William's father, was a brewer in Wurtemberg, Germany and established a brewery, in his own name, in Allegheny City in 1848. He is said to be the first person to use steam power in Pittsburgh. William became head of the Brewery when his father retired in 1870 and enlisted his brother-in-law, John P. Ober to join the company.
John P. Ober was was born August 21, 1848 in Allegheny City and starting working at his father's brewery at age fifteen where he was employed for seven years until he joined with Eberhardt. Together they ran the William Eberhardt Brewery until 1883 when they absorbed the J.N. Straub Company Brewery and incorporated as the Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company.
In 1889 the Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company allied its interests with those of the Pittsburgh Brewing Company, with which it was consolidated into in 1899. Eberhardt died a couple of weeks later, March 25, 1899. Ober became treasurer of the Pittsburgh Brewing Company and held many other offices in Pittsburgh until his death on November 11, 1909.
Pittsburgh Brewing Company continued to brew Eberhardt and Ober's "Dutch" and "Club" brands until 1952 when they were discontinued. The Eberhardt and Ober Brewery buildings on Pittsburgh's North Side are listed on the National Register of Historic Sites and have been occupied by the Pennsylvania Brewing Company since 1986.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains two series - Series I. consists of business to business correspondence regarding supplies, payments, orders, and prices and Series II. consists of receipts for goods and services including construction, beer ingredients, supplies, and employee payments. Both series are arranged by date.
Some of the materials and services included in the records relate to the purchase of hops, rice, barley, grains, corn, steam engines, coal, cork, lumber, kegs, iron work, legal matters, wagons, horses, packaging, bricklayers, dry goods, and produce.
This collection was acquired along with records of the Pittsburgh Brewing Company. Those records have been removed from this collection and added to the Records of the Pittsburgh Brewing Company, 1899-1909, ais 97:10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh as of August 2004.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Randy Liebermann, History of Technology, Arlington, Va., August 24, 1994. Color Lithograph purchased from "Between the Covers Rare Books" and added to the records in December, 2018.
Previous Citation
Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company Records, 1883-1897, AIS.1994.07, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Eberhardt Ober Brewing Company, Records, 1883-1897, ais 94:7a, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
Business and Industry; Allegheny (Pa.); Brewing industry -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny -- History; Brewers -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny -- History; Breweries -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny -- History; Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company -- History; Eberhardt, William; Ober, John Peter; Pittsburgh Brewing Company -- History
- Correspondence, 1883-1897; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I consists of business to business correspondence regarding supplies, payments, orders, and prices. The records are arranged chronologically.
  - 1883-1889 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
  - 1890-1897 (Box 1, Folder 11-22)
  - undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Receipts, 1883-1897; II.
  Series II consists of receipts for goods and services including construction, beer ingredients, supplies, and employee payments. The records are arranged chronologically.
  - 1883-1888 (Box 1, Folder 24-34)
  - 1888-1891 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - 1891-1897 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Color Lithograph (34" x 50"), Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company, Allegheny, Pennsylvania, c1885-1890 (Map-case 12 -19)